Finding Aid for Parishfield, Records 1948-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Parishfield records 1948-1971
Parishfield.
9765 Ba 2
A semi-independent agency of the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan, 1948 to 1967, with a mission of establishing a lay ministry and connect religion to the daily activities of life. Records include correspondence, administrative files, publications and photographs.
2.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group was transferred from the Episcopal Divinity School, Cambridge, Massachusetts (donor no. 8533 ) in November 1996.
The collection is open for research.
The Parishfield community, a semi-independent agency of the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan, was in existence from 1948 to 1967. Established to create a lay ministry to further the mission of the church in society, its stated purpose was to "explore, help define, and encourage the role of Christian laymen in all aspects of life." In sum, Parishfield hoped to revitalize the church by providing it with a new awareness of the critical issues facing society. Renewal was necessary, the community believed, because of the perception that faith was losing its importance in the lives of most Americans. The community sought to reconnect religion to life's daily activities to create a stronger, more aware, church. The members of the community believed that the development of a lay ministry would provide the church with such a reconnection.
From 1948 to 1967, the community management was comprised of three clergy (Rev. Francis O. Ayres, Rev. Roger Barney, and Rev. James Guinan), their families, and a deaconess (Olive Robinson). These individuals operated a lay training center in Brighton, Michigan (about 40 miles from Detroit). Parishfield considered itself a ministry of families with the assistance of advisory groups, such as the Partners for Renewal and the Advisory Committee. The group received financial support from the Episcopal Church and from solicited and unsolicited donations.
The Brighton center hosted meetings for a variety of groups ranging from members of local churches to industrial workers and professional people. In 1962, however, the community found itself moving away from an isolated concern for social and political institutions. With a desire for a more active involvement, Parishfield-Detroit was opened as a means of becoming closer to the urban society. In 1966, the church was moved completely to the Detroit office and the Brighton meeting site was closed.
During its 18 years of existence, Parishfield went through four distinct phases. The first phase lasted from 1948 to 1952 and was called the Initial Period. During this time, the community was largely introspective and spend the bulk of its time in worship, Bible study, and in discussions of the need for a lay ministry. The conclusions that resulted from these examinations were two-fold. First, the community determined that the institutional church was too isolated to affect peoples' lives in the workplace and in the political arena. Second, worship and Bible study alone will not induce Christian layman to reconnect their religious beliefs to the problems of daily life. More decisive action was needed, and this conviction led the community into the second phase of its existence.
Lasting from 1953 to 1956, this phase was entitled Industrial Groups. During this three-year period, Parishfield concentrated on the relationship between one's Christian faith and industry. Meetings focused on the growing chasm between the teachings of the church and the ethics and values of American businesses. Parishfield hoped to provide industrial employees of any level with a forum to discuss how religious values could be brought into the work place to act as a springboard for improved industrial ethics and practices. It was during this phase that Parishfield recognized the need to have a base closer to the center of Detroit. Under this premise, a former member of Parishfield opened the Detroit Industrial Mission in 1956.
The third phase, called the Christian Style of Life, lasted from 1957 to 1961. As its name implied, this phase involved discussions of what it meant for someone to be a Christian in the coming decade of the 1960s. Complementing the work begun with industrial groups, the members of Parishfield began identifying other areas where their Christian faith could be put into practice. The results, they hoped, would be a lay clergy who would reconnect the church with the daily struggles of life.
Parishfield's need to spread into new arenas led to the fourth and final phase, the Public Realm: Metropolis, beginning in 1962 with the opening of Parishfield-Detroit and ending in 1967 with the closure of the community. Parishfield-Detroit was founded on the assumption that the urban environment was the main battleground in the fight to "expand the possibilities for human life in our society." The community developed four areas in which they hoped to become "involved observers:" education, the war on poverty, community organizing, and the freedom movement. As "involved observers" Parishfield sought to become involved in community groups, without becoming captive to any idea or institution. With this goal, Parishfield hoped to act as a center of thought with a Christian orientation. It was the aim of Parishfield to understand the role of religion in life by studying the activities of laymen working in the world. During this phase, Parishfield worked closely with such groups as the Detroit Industrial Mission and People Against Racism.
From 1962 to 1966, Parishfield constantly re-evaluated the need to move the entire operation to Detroit. Meetings continued to be held in Brighton until the facility closed in 1966. Detroit became the sole home to the community until Parishfield itself disbanded in June 1, 1967. The closing came about for a couple of reasons. As the community evolved it became interested in many radical views of religion. For instance, Parishfield developed a close relationship with Paul van Buren, who often offered seminars at Parishfield. Van Buren, however, openly doubted the "supernatural" aspects of religion, and felt that these teachings acted as hindrances to the acceptance of religious life. Unsurprisingly, Parishfield's embrace of such theories led the institutional Episcopal Church to question the value of the project. As a result, the community lost essential financial and advisory support. Parishfield explains the decision to close as a recognition that the project had a shrinking influence on healing the disunification of daily life and religion.
The parishfield records are arranged in ten series:
Background Series
Publication Series
Photograph Series
Staff Series
Administrative Records Series
Correspondence Series
Groups Series
Meetings Series
Programs Series
Miscellaneous Series
The Parishfield record group, divided into ten series, documents one attempt within the Episcopal Church "to develop and promote the lay ministry through Christian experience." (Background series). The record group, in sum, concerns Parishfield as a training center for those who wanted to increase their effectiveness as Christians in understanding the issues of the day and the role that they as Christians should have in resolving societal problems. The series within the record group and the materials themselves - correspondence, meeting minutes, published matter, photographs, and other materials - document each of the four phases of the community's life. The grouping of materials into series largely reflects the Parishfield staff's concern to preserve the record of what they had accomplished.
Subjects:
Episcopal Church. Diocese of Michigan.; Detroit Industrial Mission.; Civil rights demonstrations--United States.; Lay ministry--Michigan.; Brighton (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Religious communities--Michigan--Brighton.; Religious communities--Michigan--Detroit.; Parishfield.
Contributors:
Barney, Roger.; Ayres, Francis O.; Guinan, James.; Van Buren, Paul Matthews, 1924-
Subjects - Visual Material:
Parishfield.; Brighton (Mich.); Religious facilities--Michigan--Brighton.; Religious communities--Michigan--Brighton.; Religious retreats--Michigan--Brighton.
Form and Genre terms:
Photographs.
- Background
  The Background series [4 folders] is of special interest to researchers who want to gain an understanding of Parishfield's life and mission. Materials in this series include several booklets, histories, and other informational material distributed by the community. The book project folder contains a number of historical summaries in addition to demonstrating how members of Parishfield felt about the value of the community four years after it closed. Also included are materials documenting the closing of Parishfield in 1967.
  - Close of Parishfield 1967 (Box 1)
  - Parishfield Book Plans 1971 (Box 1)
  - Parishfield Histories (Box 1)
  - Parishfield Publicity 1951-1967 (Box 1)
- Publications
  The Publication series contains issues of the community's newsletter, Sword and Shield.
  - Sword & Shield, 1957-1966 (Box 1)
  - Sword & Shield (quarterly), 1955 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series includes images of the Parishfield members at work and at worship, as well as the community's buildings in Brighton.
  - Meetings (unidentified) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous People (unidentified) (Box 1)
  - Services (unidentified) (Box 1)
  - Work on Buildings and Grounds (unidentified) (Box 1)
- Staff
  The Staff series, though small, is of interest for diary notes of Roger Barney following his move into Detroit, 1965-1966. Also of importance is the file on James Guinan, who participated in civil rights demonstrations in the Detroit area in 1963 and who worked as a civil rights worker in Mississippi in 1964. The Guinan file includes journal notes and mimeographed letters written from the South.
  - Ayres, Francis Oliver Jr. (Box 1)
  - Barney, Roger (Box 1)
  - Guinan, James (Box 1)
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative Records Series [9 folders] consists of financial records that document the community's quest for tax-exempt status and incorporation. This series contains some of the earliest material on Parishfield, dating to 1948, with the majority of the records falling within the period of the 1960s. The series also contains records relating to the closing of Parishfield in 1967.
  - Close-out turnover records 1966 (Box 1)
  - Fellowship Grant Information 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports 1957-1967 (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports, 1957-67 1961-1966 (Box 1)
  - Financial Appeals -- Combined Episcopal Services Appeal 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Financial -- Audit Reports 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Incorporation 1948 (Box 1)
  - Tax Exempt Status 1958 (Box 1)
  - Transfer to Archives 1996 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series [30 folders] documents the abundant energy of Rev. Roger Barney who involved himself both in the daily activities of Parishfield and in its relationship with those outside individuals and organizations who would learn more of what Parishfield was trying to accomplish. Included is a subseries consisting of a sampling of the day-to-day communications of the Parishfield staff with various individuals and groups.
  - Chapin, Jack and Helen 1958-1966 (Box 1)
  - Dietrich, Suzanne de 1961 (Box 1)
  - Emrich, Bishop Joe 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Green, Robert L. (Jr.) (Box 1)
  - Green, Bob and Joy 1967 (Box 1)
  - Hannahs, Gene and Agnes 1964 (Box 1)
  - Judd, Chuck and Jean 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Scott, Bob and Sally 1962-1966 (Box 1)
  - Spain, John and Jayne (Box 1)
  - Suthers, Derwent and Hannah 1962-1966 (Box 1)
  - Van Buren, Paul and Anne 1960-1966 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee
    - Kraemer, Paul and Henriette 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1962-1966 (Box 1)
    - Pelham, Joe 1964-1967 (Box 1)
    - Warrener, Harrison 1964-1966 (Box 1)
    - Winter, Gib 1958-1966 (Box 1)
  - Foreign Contacts 1961 (Box 1)
  - Partners
    - Bellucci, Robert and Tillie 1958-1963 (Box 1)
    - Black, Robert 1957-1963 (Box 1)
    - Judd, Charles M. 1957-1961 (Box 1)
    - Lloyd, Louisa 1958-1961 (Box 1)
    - McRae, John and Ruth 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - Nutter, Connie 1958-1961 (Box 1)
    - Wiley, Polly 1958-1965 (Box 1)
    - Wilcox, Bill and Faith 1958-1965 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous: A-Z, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Groups
  The Groups series [7 folders] contains materials representing Parishfield's working relationships with a variety of groups, both religious and secular. Partners for Renewal and the Advisory Committee were both internal groups involved with the funding and administration of Parishfield. The folders regarding these internal support groups are especially helpful as they contain in-depth writings on the success of meetings and the state of the Parishfield Community at various stages in its development. Other groups were external to the community, though some (such as the Church Army) used the Parishfield facilities for meetings and programs. The records in these files consist primarily of notes and correspondence reflecting the relationship between Parishfield and the groups.
  - Advisory Committee 1962-1966 (Box 2)
  - Church Army 1952-1961 (Box 2)
  - Citizens for Fair Use Enforcement 1966 (Box 2)
  - Columbus Group 1963-1966 (Box 2)
  - Partners for Renewal
    - Correspondence and Background 1952-1961 (Box 2)
    - Member Information 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - Study Materials 1958 (Box 2)
- Meetings
  There are two subseries to the Meetings series [21 folders]. The first documents the regular meetings of Parishfield members; the second documents the special meetings. Included are meeting minutes, correspondence, summaries, and background information.
  - Regular Meetings (Box 2)
    - Numbered Files
      - 1957-1958 #1-24 (Box 2)
      - #25-46 1958-1959 (Box 2)
      - #47-6021 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      - #6022-6116 1960-1961 (Box 2)
      - #6118-6227 1961-1962 (Box 2)
    - Staff Meeting Notes & Calendars 1957 (Box 2)
    - Summaries of meetings 1957-1965 (Box 2)
      (card file located in Box 3)
  - Special Meetings
    - Advisory Committee Reports 1959-1965 (Box 2)
    - Automation/Cybernation #655 1965 (Box 2)
    - Christianity and Industry 1954 (Box 2)
    - Community 1959-1962 (Box 2)
    - Conference for Institutional Chaplains 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - Conference on Radical Theology 1966 (Box 2)
    - Consultation on Mission 1959 (Box 2)
    - Corrections and Probationers 1957-1963 (Box 2)
    - Cranbrook Industrial Study Group 1959-1962 (Box 2)
    - Ministry of the Laity (Box 2)
    - Nursing and Nursing Education 1961 (Box 2)
    - Paul van Buren #6412 1964 (Box 2)
    - Meeting on Religion and Corrections (Box 2)
    - William Hamilton 1966 (Box 2)
- Programs
  Much of Parishfield's social activism during the 1960s is reflected in the records of the Programs series [9 folders]. Of particular interest is the material from the Detroit Industrial Mission, which includes newsletters, minutes, the report "Mission to Metropolis," and records from the Institute Detroit Parishfield, a special project that formed from Parishfield's work with DIM.
  - Community Organizing 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - Consultations - Episcopal Nativity Church 1961-1967 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Industrial Mission
    - Institute Detroit Parishfield (IDP) 1958-1961 (Box 2)
    - "Mission to Metropolis" 1964 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters 1958-1967 (Box 2)
    - Writings, Minutes, Miscellaneous 1957-1966 (Box 2)
  - Inner City Organizing Committee 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Men & Women Abroad 1957-1960 (Box 2)
  - Summaries (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series includes the membership card file, sermons, and various writings.
  - Sermons 1963-1965 (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Home Department Project, editing work 1966 (Box 2)
  - Bible Study -- Study Guide (Box 2)
  - Membership Card File (Box 3)